hey what's up guys my name is the Cho
and welcome back to my C++ Series today
we're going to be talking about
references last week we talked about
pointers so if you didn't see that video
you are 100% going to have to because
references are really just an extension
of pointers so you need to be able to
understand at least at a basic level how
pointers work in order to actually get
this video so go ahead there'll be a
link in the description below if you
haven't seen the pointers video
definitely watch that okay so pointers
and references are two kind of keywords
that are tossed around a lot in C++ and
other languages uh they're essentially
the same thing though I just want to
start this video by saying that pointers
and references are pretty much the same
thing as far as what the computer will
actually do with them now semantically
so how we actually use them and how we
write them there are some subtle
differences but at the end of the day
references are just pointers usually in
Disguise that's just all they are it's
just syntax sugar on top of pointers to
make it a little bit easier to read and
a little bit easier to follow a
reference is essentially exactly what it
sounds like it's a way for us to
reference an existing variable unlike a
pointer where you could create a new
pointer variable and then set it equal
to null pointer or something like that
set it equal to zero you can't do that
with references because references have
to reference an already existing
variable references themselves are not
new variables They Don't Really occupy
memory they don't really have storage
they're not like your typical variable
because what they are in instead is a
reference to a variable I'm going to be
bringing up a few different examples in
this video however I'm going to keep it
brief because references aren't that
complicated and the best way really to
learn how to use them is actually to
start using them so as the series goes
on we'll be using them all the time and
you'll see what kind of the best
practice is or at least my opinion on
what the best practice is uh to do with
references however if we jump into some
code let's say that I make a variable
I'll call it a and I'll set it equal to
5 it's just going to be an integer if I
want to create a reference to that
variable I can do so by typing in the
type of the variable followed by an
ampersand note here that the Ampersand
is actually part of the variable
declaration in the previous video about
pointers we learned that if we create a
pointer uh we can use the Ampersand
operator here to actually take the
memory address of an existing variable
it's different here because the
Ampersand is actually part of the type
it's not you can see it's not actually
next to an existing variable it's part
of the type so just note that difference
because with a lot of people as soon as
you see an ampan and they think oh it's
a reference or oh it's definitely an
address off it's kind of depending on
context here so in this case because
it's next to the type it's a reference
so if we keep writing this I'll call
this ref and I'll set this equal to a
and that's really all you have to do
there's no kind of weird operator or
something that we have to use here we
just set it equal to an existing
variable and so what we've done now is
we've essentially created something
called an alias because this ref
variable I say variable in quotes here
because it's not really a variable it's
just a a reference like this ref
variable doesn't actually exist it just
exists in our source code if you compile
this code right now you're not going to
get two variables created a and ref
you're just going to have a what we can
do now is we can use ref as if it was a
so if we set ref now equal to 2 and then
print
a if we run our program here you're
going to see that a is equal to 2 now
because we're printing a and we've just
changed ref to two because for all
intents and purposes ref is a we've just
created an alias for a and in this case
our reference isn't a pointer or
anything like that there's no need for
the compiler to actually create a new
variable if you compile this code it's
just going to act as if we just set a to
two because that's really what we did
this is just something that we can write
in our source code to make our lives
easier if we wish to Alias a variable
now let's try something a little bit
more complicated suppose that we wanted
to write a function which was supposed
to increment an integer if we just write
the function like
this and then do something like value ++
what will actually happen is if I create
my integer over here and then I call
increment with a as the parameter what's
going to happen here is since we are
just passing this by value you can see
that we're not passing this as a pointer
or as a reference or anything like that
it's actually going to copy this value 5
into this function just copy it's going
to create a brand new variable called
value with that so it's almost as if we
were to write something like that that's
exactly what will happen so instead of
that and I can prove it of course if I
just run my code here and we log this
we're actually going to still end up
with five printing to the console which
you can see over here what I need to do
is I actually need to pass this variable
by reference in order for it to
increment because what I really want to
do is I want to actually affect this
variable here so how can I achieve that
how can I actually modify this variable
by passing it into a function now last
time we talked about pointers and
remember pointers are memory addresses
so theoretically I hope you're putting
this together in your mind cuz it's so
exciting but theoretically what we could
do if we were really ever right is we
could instead of passing the actual
value five into that function we could
pass the memory address of this a
variable because then what we can do in
that function is we can look up that
memory address see that value five and
then just modify that that memory
address we can write to that memory
address since we've passed that memory
address into the function so let's give
that a shot what I'll do is I'll modify
this to actually take in a pointer and
I'll just I'll still call it value and
then what I'll do here in increment is
I'll pass the memory address of a in
instead of just the value five it's now
passing the memory address of this
variable one more thing I'll have to do
is actually dreference this value so
that we can actually write to that
memory instead of modifying the pointer
itself if I just do this without the D
reference it's going to just increment
that address right so a pointer of
course just a memory address just an
integer and if I do value Plus+ without
the asterisk without the D reference
operator then it is just going to in
increment my memory address not the
actual value there now because of the
order of operations it's it's actually
going to do the increment first and then
D reference so what I want to do instead
is D reference first and then increment
because I don't want to increment the
pointer and then dreference it I want to
dreference the pointer first and then
increment the value at the pointer so if
I compile this code and run it you will
see that I will get the value six
printing so awesome we've successfully
managed to pass a variable by reference
into a function however this video is
about references so we can do exactly
what we just did here a lot easier with
less code and with less kind of
decorating our syntax if we just use a
reference and that's what I would do in
this situation I would use a reference
so what we can do is rewrite this to
take in a reference instead of a pointer
and then what that means is that I lose
this whole need of D referencing I can
change this back to exactly what it was
and then over here I don't need to pass
the memory address of a I can just pass
in a and since it is being passed by
reference we've basically Rewritten the
code to do exactly the same thing
internally when it gets compiled it will
be exactly the same as what we've
written before however this time it just
looks nicer in our source code again
that's the only difference if I run my
program you can see we get six so that
is all that references really are they
are just syntax sugar references there
is nothing you can do with a reference
that you cannot do with a pointer
pointers are like references except
they're even more useful and they're
even more powerful however if you can
get away with using a reference like
what we just did here absolutely use a
reference because it's going to be a lot
cleaner and simpler to read not that
pointers are really really difficult to
read but it will look a lot cleaner in
your source code one other important
thing that I want to mention with
references is that once you declare a
reference you cannot change what it
references what I mean by that is that
suppose that I had two integers I Had A
and B and B was set to eight a was set
to five and then what I wanted to do is
declare a reference that was set to a
and then maybe later on in my code I
decided oh actually you know what I want
to set my reference to be referencing B
can I do something like that the answer
is no you can't do that what will happen
in this case is that it will effectively
create a reference to a and then when
you decide to set that reference equal
to B it will just set a equal to the
value of B which is 8 so what you will
end up with here is a being equal to 8
and B being equal to 8 that is that's it
that's what you'll get and of course
because of that that also means that
when you declare a reference you need to
actually assign it to something you
cannot just do this you can see that the
compiler will not let you do that it
requires an initializer when you declare
a reference you have to immediately
assign it to something because it has to
reference something because remember
it's not really a real variable it's a
reference so in this example
specifically what would I do if I
actually wanted this kind of
functionality if I wanted to actually
change what ref was a reference of well
of course as I mentioned earlier this
isn't a real variable we would need to
create some kind of variable of sorts
that we could set up to point a first
and then later on we could switch it to
point to B and of course I keep saying
the word point in the hopes that you'll
understand that I'm talking about a
pointer so instead of this let's just
make this a pointer we can initially set
it to the memory address of a and then
when I wanted to switch to it being
pointing to B
I can just switch it like this because
remember to actually start affecting the
value that this pointer is pointing to I
need to dreference the pointer first and
then set it equal to something like this
so in this case I'm setting a equal to 2
and in this case I'm setting b equal to
1 and if I was to log both of
these they should be 2 and one and you
can see that they are all right that's
pretty much all I want to say really
simple stuff we'll be using references a
lot more in the future again they're one
of those things that you just use all
the time like pointers so you'll see a
lot more examples down the road as this
series progresses if you enjoy this
video please hit the like button you can
follow me on Twitter and Instagram and
of course if you really enjoyed this
video you can support me on patreon to
make sure that I can continue these C++
series videos and make more awesome
videos in the future all right next
time next time we're going to kick it up
and not I'll see you guys later goodbye
[Music]